JUAN CARLOS URCIA BAREA

jcurciabarea@gmail.com · www.jcurciabarea.info

I am a motivated, diligent analyst with a passion for macroeconomics, finance, and political economy. My current work at Moody's Investors Service focuses on sovereign credit risk for governments in Latin America. I previously served as policy advisor to U.S. Senator Ben Cardin in Washington, D.C. My skillset centers on economic and policy analysis, communication, and constantly learning.

EDUCATION

Princeton UniversityPrinceton, NJMaster in Public Affairs | School of Public and International AffairsAugust 2020 to May 2022

Brown University
Providence, RI
Bachelor of Arts | History
August 2013 to May 2017

EMPLOYMENT

Moody's Investors Service

New York, NY

Ratings Associate | Sovereign Risk Group

July 2022 to Present

- Research and analyze the credit risk of government debt issuers including Argentina, Costa Rica, Guatemala, Honduras, and Panama, focusing on macroeconomics, government finance, and political developments.
- Develop and write research publications covering relevant credit developments such as election results, government revenue strategies, and economic developments, in addition to credit profile overviews.
- Support sector-wide projects including frontier market and multilateral development bank outlooks.
- Collect, manage, and analyze economic and financial data for sovereigns.
- Interface with government officials, investors, and clients, representing the company in work trips to issuer countries such as Guatemala and Panama, as well as at conferences such as the IMF Spring Meetings.

U.S. Department of Commerce

Princeton, NJ

Graduate Consultant | Office of the U.S. Secretary of Commerce

August 2021 to January 2022

- Graduate capstone project to advise the Office of the Secretary on implementation of the CHIPS Act.
- Developed recommendations for the creation of the National Semiconductor Technology Center (NSTC) by researching and analyzing industry trends, interviewing leading firms, academics, and defense analysts.
- Led visual design of the team's capstone report in Adobe InDesign.

U.S. Department of the Treasury

Washington, DC

Graduate Intern | Office of International Financial Markets

May to August 2021

- Created a heatmap dashboard in Excel tracking macroeconomic and financial risk indicators across various advanced economies and emerging markets, pulling data from Haver Analytics.
- Drafted internal memos reviewing trends such as sovereign-bank debt nexus, housing market activity, credit and asset prices as indicators of bubbles, and sovereign dollar debt crises.

U.S. Senator Benjamin L. Cardin

Washington, DC

Legislative Correspondent

July 2018 to July 2020

Staff Assistant

September 2017 to June 2018

- Assisted in writing and managing legislation, including the Government Employee Fair Treatment Act (P.L.116-1), which became law guaranteeing back-pay for furloughed workers during government shutdowns.
- Led office research and recommendations on the 2018-2019 35-day federal government shutdown and COVID-19 unemployment insurance and state fiscal relief legislative efforts as part of the CARES Act.
- Researched and wrote recommendation memos for bills, resolutions, nominations, Dear Colleague letters, constituent issues, breaking developments, and other action items for the Senator.
- Prepared and staffed the Senator for hearings and other developments before the U.S. Senate Committee on Finance and the U.S. Senate Committee on Environment and Public Works.
- Advised press team on policy issues and helped draft and edit press releases and statements.
- Wrote speeches, floor statements, and constituent responses on legislative efforts and political issues.
- Represented the Senator in meetings with stakeholders and political nominees.

U.S. Senate Committee on Foreign Relations

Intern | Ranking Member, Democratic Staff

July to August 2016

Washington, DC

- Researched and circulated press clips on Southeast Asia security and foreign aid issues.
- Helped prepare staff and members for committee hearings, meetings, and external events.

U.S. Representative David N. Cicilline

Pawtucket, RI

May to July 2016

Intern | Pawtucket District Office

- Managed busy front office, supervised 10 events in the district, and logged constituent correspondence.
- Created an Excel database for major government and elected officials in Rhode Island for internal office use.

The Walt Disney Company

Burbank, CA

Intern | Corporate Strategy and Business Development

June to August 2015

- Conducted a financial analysis of a merger between two telecommunications firms.
- Collaborated on group research and slide deck on the "smart" ad tech industry landscape.

VOLUNTEERING AND COMMUNITY ACTIVITIES

Instituto Cervantes | Member and Student (2023-Present)

• Study the Spanish language and participate in Spanish and Latin American cultural events and activities.

Volunteer Income Tax Assistance (VITA) | SPIA Chapter Co-Lead and Volunteer (2021-2022)

• Provided weekly tax filing services to low-income and disadvantaged residents of Mercer County, New Jersey.

SPIA First Generation and Low-Income (FLI) Students | Co-Lead and Co-Founder (2020-2022)

• Hosted FLI alumni for career talks and collaborate with university on programming for FLI students.

The Julis-Rabinowitz Center for Public Policy and Finance | Graduate Associate (2020-2022)

• Engaged in seminars on financial policy and economic history led by faculty and visiting experts.

Congressional Hispanic Staff Association (CHSA) | Alumnus (2016-2020)

• Participated in career development, networking, and volunteering activities.

LANGUAGES AND NATIONALITIES

- English: Native/Fluent | Spanish: Advanced | Japanese: Novice
- United States of America (citizen) | Spain (citizen)

RELEVANT GRADUATE COURSEWORK

Economics and Finance Microeconomics — Professor Amy Craft Macroeconomics — Professor Gregor Jarosch Public Economics — Professor Henrik Kleven International Economics — Professor Silvia Weyerbrock Financial Management — Professor Adam Shrager Growth, Finance, Crises — Professor Ashoka Mody Macroeconomic Ideas — Professor Ashoka Mody Central Banking — Professor Alan Blinder Global Supply Chains — Professor Doyle Hodges

Statistics

Quantitative Analysis – Professor David Lee Econometrics I – Professor Jordan Matsudaira Econometrics II – Professor Alexandre Mas Program & Policy Evaluation – Professor Jean Grossman

Politics

Politics of Public Policy – Professor Andrew Moravcsik Domestic Politics – Professor Frances Lee The State – Professor Philip Pettit

SKILLS AND INTERESTS

Professional: politics, economics, financial analysis, fiscal and debt metrics, statistical analysis, data visualization, graphic design, writing, editing, public speaking, event planning, customer service

Software: Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Outlook); Adobe Creative Suite (Photoshop, InDesign); Econometric Analysis (Stata, R); Financial Research (Bloomberg Terminal, Haver Analytics, FactSet, Reuters); Programming (Python, Java, HTML/CSS); Communications (Slack, Signal, Zoom, Webex, Teams)

Policy: macroeconomics, fiscal and monetary policy, financial markets, banking, international affairs, globalization, poverty alleviation and social safety net, labor and unions, wealth and income inequality

Interests: photography, drawing, sudoku, computers, political and economic history, hiking, tennis, soccer